<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>https://kamhawinotes.com/</title>
   
   <link>http://localhost:4000</link>
   <description>The blog of Mohamed Elkamhawi</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Mohamed Elkamhawi</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>Autonomous Vehicles: The Next Disruptive Technology</title>
	  <link>//Autonomous-Vehicles</link>
	  <author>Mohamed Elkamhawi</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-06-02T13:33:33+02:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//Autonomous-Vehicles</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>The ultimate goal of the tech industry is to eliminate routine, turning the
human attention away from repetitive tasks, to focus on creative ones.</p>

<p>This isn’t new, History is full of examples of developing tools to help
make accomplishing tasks easier, and usually the technological advancement creates
new unimagined markets, the invention of the printing press in 1440 is a clear
example, while it destroyed one of the oldest crafts (Hand copying books), it
created new professions no one imagined were needed, such as journalism, book
publishing &amp; distribution.</p>

<p>This is why disruption is important, it is actually a need, introducing new
technologies that completely transforms the economy is a sign of the advancement
of the human race.</p>

<p>Creating the autonomous vehicle is going to cause social, political, and economic
disruptions of massive scales. not all the consequences are clear now, what is
clear is that the transportation sector as well as the car manufacturing sector
have reached the point of saturation long ago.</p>

<p>Car companies today compete in reducing prices, having a wider distribution
network, and joining new markets. the product itself sees no innovation, within
the same price range all models across different companies are similar. the same
thing happened in the transportation sector, with the exception of ride sharing
apps, the whole market competes in reducing profit margins and costs to reduce
prices, but no real innovation.</p>

<p>Different players from both sectors (Transportation &amp; Car manufacturing)
are now racing to reach the same goal: getting rid of the steering wheel. Startups are
emerging, old companies are <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/ford-is-no-longer-a-car-company-2017-5" target="_blank">restructuring</a>,
whoever reaches this goal first will not only strike a gold mine, but will
change the way humans live forever.</p>

<p>What is clear now is that developing self-driving vehicles will cause these
two sectors to merge into one. car companies will no longer sell cars to consumers,
nobody will need to own a car, instead people will summon cars using their mobile
phones. cars will patrol the streets dropping off one customer to go to another.
there are already some <a href="http://www.cnbc.com/2017/05/23/reporters-notebook-be-warned-us25-oil-is-coming-and-along-with-it-a-new-world-order.html" target="_blank">estimates</a> that using robot-taxis will be 10x cheaper than owning
a car.</p>

<p>Eliminating the human factor will result in safer trips, the rate of accidents
is going to drop significantly. this goal alone is enough to encourage people to
invest in developing this technology.</p>

<p>The shipping sector is going to be affected as well, with autonomous trucks moving
goods 24/7 between countries, shipping costs will drop and goods will reach their
destinations faster.</p>

<p>Another thing that is going to change is the absurd notion that every one should
have his/her own car. Fewer cars will serve more people, resulting in fewer street
congestions, less time on the road and higher productivity.</p>

<p><em>Transport As A Service (TAAS)</em> is going to be the norm. granted, a lot of people
will lose their jobs, mainly drivers as well as people working in the vehicle distribution
sector. but new sectors will emerge, new jobs will be created, and people will
enjoy less routine and more life.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
